Guide to the Leo L. Stanley Diaries
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Leo L. Stanley diaries
1918-1968
SC0070
Stanley, Leo L. (Leo Leonidas), b. 1886
Stanley, Leo L.,, 1886-
6 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Dr. Leo L. Stanley.
Information about Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Biography
Leo L. Stanley, born 1886 in Oregon, graduated from Cooper Medical College of Stanford University in 1912. He spent most of his life as Chief Physician and Surgeon at the California State Prison at San Quentin. He did take time out to travel, however, usually as the ship's doctor on large luxury cruises.
Scope and Content of Collection
Diaries are written in the form of a daily log and include photographs, menus, passenger lists, ship's newspapers, maps, programs, trip literature, newspaper articles, and some correspondence. Also included are some case histories of various men he had known in prison. The travel books concentrate mainly on the local color of the places visited. Those from his 1934 trip through Russia and Siberia also include information on the government institutions he visited. The collection also includes some medical articles by Stanley and autobiographical articles.
Access Terms
Stanford Alumni Association; Stanley, Leo L.,, 1886-; East Asia.; France--Description and travel.; Germany--Description and travel.; Mexico--Description and travel.; South America--Description and travel.; Soviet Union--Description and travel.; United States--Description and travel.
Collection Contents
- "The Sixth Voyage of the Sachem", July 8 - Aug. 1, 1918 (Box 1)
  Round trip cruise from San Francisco to Honolulu, on which Dr. Stanley is ship's surgeon.
- "To Ellis Island and Back", Sept. 1920 (Box 1)
  Round trip by railroad from San Francisco to Ellis Island, NY. Dr. Stanley serves as physician for undesirable aliens, either criminal, insane, or guilty of illegal entry into the United States, who are being brought by train to New York to be deported to their native countries.
- "Trot, Trot, Trot to Boston", May 21-Apr 11, 1921 (Box 1)
  Dr. Stanley serves as physician for undesirable aliens, either criminal, insane, or guilty of illegal entry into the United States, who are being brought by train to New York to be deported to their native countries. This volume includes an extra trip to Boston.
- "Five Weeks Leave", 1922 (Box 1)
  Deportation train, San Francisco to New York. Dr. Stanley then attended meeting of the association for the Study of Internal Secretions in St. Louis.
- South American Cruise, 1928
  Dr. Stanley was the ship's doctor on the S.S. City of Los Angeles cruise around South America.
  - (South American Cruise I), Oct. 4-24, 1928 (Box 1)
    Preparation for voyage; departure; itinerary includes Callao and Lima, Peru; Valparaiso and Santiago, Chile.
  - (South American Cruise II), Oct. 25 - Nov. 10, 1928 (Box 1)
    Itinerary includes Straits of Magellan; Punta Arenas; Buenos Aires, Argentina; Montevideo, Uruguay; Santos and Sao Paulo, Brazil.
  - (South American Cruise III), Nov. 11 - Dec. 6, 1928 (Box 1)
    Itinerary includes Rio de Janeiro, Brazil; Port of Spain, Trinidad, BWI; La Guayra and Caracas, Venezuela; Panama Canal Zone; Salvador; Guatemala; Mazetlan, Mexico.
- All Pacific Cruise, 1929
  Dr. Stanley was the ship's doctor on the S.S. Malolo.
  - Japan (v. I), Jan. 14-Oct. 3, 1929 (Box 1)
    This volume covers his departure.
  - Japan (v. II), Oct. 4-12, 1929 (Box 1)
    Itinerary includes Yokohama, Tokyo, Kobe, Nara, Miyajima.
  - China (v. III), Oct. 14-22, 1929 (Box 1)
    Itinerary includes Chinwangtao, Peiping, Great Wall, Shanghaikuan.
  - Hong Kong, Manila, Saigon (v. IV), Oct. 23 - Nov. 2, 1929 (Box 1)
    Itinerary includes Hong Kong, Kowloon, Canton, Manila, Saigon.
  - Siam, Singapore, Java (v. V), Nov. 3-11, 1929 (Box 2)
    Itinerary includes Bangkok; Singapore; Jahore; Batavia, Java; Buitenzorg, Java; Tanjong Priok.
  - Australia (v. VI), Nov. 12-28, 1929 (Box 2)
    Itinerary includes Rottnest Island, Fremantle, Perth, Melbourne, Sydney, Katoomba.
  - New Zealand, Fijis, Samoa, Hawaii (v. VII), Nov. 29-Dec. 15, 1929 (Box 2)
    Itinerary includes Auckland; Suva, Fijis; Pago Pago, Samoa; Honolulu and Hilo, Hawaii.
- North Cape Russia Cruise, 1931
  Dr. Stanley was a passenger on the S. S. Carinthia.
  - North Cape Russia Cruise (v. I), June 26-July 8, 1931 (Box 2)
    Covers his arrival in New York by train and stop at Reykjavik, Iceland.
  - North Cape Russia Cruise (v. II), July 9-18, 1931 (Box 2)
    Itinerary includes Hammerfest, Lyngen,Trondhjem, and Bergen in Norway.
  - North Cape Russia Cruise (v. III), July 19-Aug. 1, 1931 (Box 2)
    Itinerary includes Oslo, Visby, Gottland, Stockholm. At Stockholm, Doctor Stanley discontinued the cruise and stayed in Stockholm with a sick passenger, his friend, Mrs. Aubrey Montgomery, known as 'Lady Bob," whom he had known on other cruises. This volume also contains her will. Returns via the Suecia and the S. S. Mauretania to New York, then by train to San Francisco.
- Around the World, 1934
  On this trip Dr. Stanley served as physician for deportees on a train from San Francisco to New York, continuing as a passenger to Russia to study hospitals and prisons there. Included are photographs of and comments on the institutions he visited.
  - Across America (v. I), Apr. 20-May 8, 1934 (Box 2)
    San Francisco to New York on deportation train; from New York on the President Roosevelt, bound for le Havre.
  - France, Germany (v. II), May 9-18, 1934 (Box 2)
    Itinerary includes Berlin and Potsdam; airplane from Berlin to Leningrad.
  - Russia/Siberia (v. III), May 19-30, 1934 (Box 3)
    Leningrad and Moscow. Dr. Stanley visits and describes a penal colony outside Moscow and a childcare center in Leningrad for working mothers, also a clinic for working mothers. The penal colony is an experimental commune for prisoners selected from other penitentiaries. Train across Siberia to Vologda, Omsk, Zima, Baikal; visits hospitals and prisons. Also includes excerpts from the "Guide Book to the Soviet Union."
  - Manchoukuo (v. IV), May 31-June 3, 1934 (Box 3)
    Chinese Eastern Railway to Tsitsihar, Anda, Harbin, Hsinking, Mukden in Manchuria and Shanhaikuan in China.
    [There is no volume 22.]
  - China (v. V), June 4-8, 1934 (Box 3)
    Itinerary includes Peiping, Tientsin, Nanking, Shanghai. Boards the M.S. Chichibu Maru.
  - Japan, Hawaii (v. VI), June 9-22, 1934 (Box 3)
    On M.S. Chichibu Maru; itinerary includes Kobe, Kyoto, Yokohama, Pearl Harbor, San Francisco. Visits Oahu Prison and Palama Settlement in Hawaii.
- Mediterranean Cruise, 1935
  Dr. Stanley serves as physician on a deportation train to New York, then goes as a passenger to the Mediterranean on the S. S. Statendam.
  - Mediterranean Cruise (v. I), Jan. 28-Feb. 16, 1935 (Box 3)
    Chapters 1-5. Deportation train leaves San Francisco for New York. Includes case histories of passengers. Itinerary includes Los Angeles, Yuma, El Paso, San Antonia, Houston.
    Chapters 6-13. S. S. Statendam leaves NY. Contains letter and poem from a prisoner at San Quentin, the famous J. P. "Bluebeard" Watson, who murdered 15 women. Itinerary includes on the Atlantic, at sea, Funchal, Madeira, Gibraltar, La Linea.
  - Mediterranean Cruise (v. II), Feb. 17-26, 1935 (Box 3)
    Chapters 14-21. Itinerary includes Cadiz - Seville, Tangier - Malaga, Algiers, Palma, Mallorca, Cannes, Malta, coast and ancient Apollonia viewed from Statendam.
  - Mediterranean Cruise (v. III), Feb. 27-Mar. 8, 1935 (Box 3)
    Chapters 22-31. Itinerary includes Egypt, Holy Land, Jerusalem, Beirut, Syria.
  - Mediterranean Cruise (v. IV), Mar. 9 - 17, 1935 (Box 3)
    Chapters 32-40. Itinerary includes Rhodes, Dardanelles, Istanbul, Bosporus, Black Sea, Athens, Corfu, Jugoslavia, Venice.
  - Mediterranean Cruise (v. V), Mar. 19-29, 1935 (Box 3)
    Chapters 41-47. Itinerary includes Sicily, Messina, Taormina, Naples, Pompei, Mt. Vesuvius, Island of Elba, Monte Carlo, Monaco, The Riviera, Nice; and in Holland, Rotterdam, Delft, The Hague, Aalsmeer, Amsterdam, Edam, Volendam, Zuyder Zee, Utrech.
- Around the World on a Dollar, 1936
  Dr. Stanley was ship's doctor on the S. S. President Harrison of the Dollar Steamship Lines.
  - Around the World on a Dollar (v. I), Oct. 8 - Nov. 8, 1936 (Box 4)
    Summary of previous trips. Preparation and departure. Honolulu, Kobe, Shanghai, Kowloon, Hong Kong.
  - Around the World on a Dollar (v. II), Nov. 9-29, 1936 (Box 4)
    Itinerary includes Manila, Singapore, Island of Penang, Ceylon, Bombay.
  - Around the World on a Dollar (v. III), Dec. 5, 1936-Jan. 12, 1937 (Box 4)
    Itinerary includes Red Sea, Gulf of Suez, Cairo, Alexandria (by train), Naples, Genoa, Marseilles, Gibraltar, New York. Travel to Flint, Michigan by train, San Francisco by car.
- Mixing in Mexico, 1937
  Dr. Stanley took a train trip to Guadalajara for the meeting of Pacific Association of Railway Surgeons, October 8-9, 1937, and then a pack trip into the countryside.
  - Mixing in Mexico (v. I), June - Oct. 11, 1937 (Box 4)
    Diary includes correspondence regarding the meeting and covers the train to Guadalajara and pack trip to Juanacatlan, San Juan.
  - Mixing in Mexico (v. II), Oct. 12-19, 1937 (Box 4)
    Itinerary includes Jocotpec, San Luis Soyatlan, Tuscueca, Chapala, Tepic, Culiacan, Nogales, and back.
- American President Lines Cruises, 1959-1963
  Volumes 35-1 through 36-2 are paperbound travel logs of cruises to the Orient on the American President Lines on which Dr. Stanley served as ship's doctor. In almost all of these cruises, the itinerary was: San Francisco, Honolulu, Yokohama, Hong Kong, Manila, Hong Kong, Kobe, Yokohama and/or Kowloon, Honolulu, San Francisco.
  - S. S. President Wilson, April 5 - May 19, 1959 (Box 5)
  - S. S. President Wilson, Sept. 4 -Nov. 15, 1959 (Box 5)
  - S. S. President Hoover, Nov. 7 -Dec. 19, 1961 (Box 5)
  - S. S. President Wilson, Apr. 24 -June 3, 1961 (Box 5)
  - S. S. President Hoover, June 15 -July 29, 1961 (Box 5)
  - S. S. President Hoover (includes a stop in Okinawa), Aug. 29 - Oct. 9, 1962 (Box 5)
  - S. S. President Cleveland, Oct. 28 - Dec. 1962 (Box 5)
  - S. S. President Cleveland, May - June, 1963 (Box 6)
  - S. S. President Roosevelt, Oct. 1 - Nov. 11, 1963 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous Diaries, 1920-1965
  - Medical Articles by Stanley, 1920-1930 (Box 6)
  - Medical Articles by Stanley, 1930-1940 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous articles by Stanley from The Centaur, 1941-1960 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper articles by Stanley in the San Miguel Banner, Sept. - Oct. 1965 (Box 6)
  - Maps, correspondence, ship paraphernalia, and newspaper articles about and/or by Stanley (Box 6)